Louis Lozowick Papers
Louis Lozowick Papers
1922-1974
Lozowick, Louis, 1892-1973.
3.75 linear ft.
Papers of the American Jewish lithographer, painter, and art critic, born in Russia, emigrated to the United States in 1906. Correspondence (1923-1973); manuscript writings, including various chapters of an unpublished autobiography; photographs and reproductions of Lozowick's work; and printed material, including articles by Lozowick and exhibition catalogs.
149142
Biographical History
Louis Lozowick (1892-1973) was a Ukrainian-American artist. Though he began his artistic career as a painter, he is best known for his lithographs of skyscrapers, constructions, and machinery.
He attended the Kiev Art School from 1904 to 1906 and emigrated to the United States at age 14 -- a tricky achievement since he came without passport or papers. Once in New York he took a series of factory jobs to pay for his art studies at the National Academy of Design (1912-1915) with Carlson, Leon Kroll, and others. In 1915 he entered Ohio State University, graduating in three years as a Phi Beta Kappa. In 1919, after a brief stint in the military, he left the United States to travel extensively throughout Europe, studying art and supporting himself by writing articles for various European publications.
Almost immediately upon his return to the United States, he began his "Machine Ornament" series, exploring the straight lines, contrasting light and shadow, and geometrical patterns of the urban landscape that would fascinate him for the next fifty years. In 1924 he had an exhibit at the New Art Circle and then another at Weyhe's; both Weyhe and Carl Zigrosser, then head of the gallery, encouraged Lozowick in his focus on the graphic arts. The young artist had a number of exhibits of his lithographs over the next few years at Weyhe's and at Whitney Studio on West 8th Street including his "Machine Age Exposition" in 1927. Throughout his career the complex architecture of the urban landscape -- bridges, scaffolding, train tracks, skyscrapers -- continued to intrigue him (though nature appears more frequently in pieces from his later years).
During the Depression Lozowick, like many of his fellow artists, created murals and prints for the WPA including a mural for the New York City General Post Office (1936). In 1931 he married Adele Turner, and in 1943 the couple moved to New Jersey where Lozowick remained for the rest of his career.
Lozowick was recognized several times during his career for the quality of his work. He received the Brewster Prize for lithography at the Chicago Art Institute (1929), first prize for lithography at the Philadelphia Art Alliance (1930), and first prize (and an award of $1,000) at the International Print Competition (1931). Hoboken, one of his lithographs, was included in the fifty best prints of the year by the American Institute of Graphic Arts (1929) and his work has since been included in several annual collections of best prints. His work is in the permanent collections of several museums including the National Gallery of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco, U.S. Library of Congress, and Smithsonian American Art Museum.
In addition to his accomplishments as a practicing artist, he taught at the American Art School in New York City for several years, was considered something of an authority on modern Russian art, designed stage sets for a production at the Goodman Theatre in Chicago, and wrote extensively on the theatre. He was a member of the American Society of Painters, Sculptors, and Gravers, the American Artists Congress, An American Group, Inc., and American Print Makers.
Lozowick died in New Jersey in 1973.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1922 to 1974, the Louis Lozowick Papers comprises correspondence, photographs and reproductions of his artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Russian-American painter, lithographer, and art critic (1892-1973). While focusing on his professional career, the collection also reveals aspects of Lozowick's personal life, particularly his attachment to his ethnic origins and his political and religious philosophy as a Jewish artist and writer.
Arranged chronologically, the predominantly incoming Correspondence (Box 1) reflects Lozowick's artistic, ethnic, political, and religious associations. Correspondents include art historians and curators (Erwin O. Christensen, Karl Schwarz, Carl Zigrosser) artists (John Taylor Arms, George Biddle, David Burliuk, Marc Chagall, Howard Cook, Arthur Crisp, Stuart Davis, Katherine S. Dreier, Fritz Eichenberg, Ralph Fabri, Fernand Leger, Howard Mandel, Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, Lynd Ward, Max Weber, Art Young); authors (Louis Adamic, Newton Arvin, V. F. Calverton, Waldo Frank, Langston Hughes, Bernhard J. Stern) and editors (Milton A. Abernethy, Jack Conroy, Jay Du Von, Henry Hurwitz, Samuel Putnam). Organizational correspondence includes that of cultural organizations (American Federation of Arts, American Russian Institute, the Municipal Art Committee); galleries and museums (Art Association of Indianapolis, Indiana, Art Institute of Chicago, Berkshire Museum, Museum of Modern Art, Museum Tel-Aviv, New Jersey State Museum, Newark Museum, Norfolk Museum, Oakland Art Gallery, Walker Art Center); governmental agencies (Federal Art Project, U. S. Treasury Department); political groups (Ad Hoc Committee to Lift Ban on The Nation, National Committee to Aid Striking Miners Fighting Starvation); professional organizations (American Society of Painters, Sculptors and Gravers, Artists for Victory, Inc., National Academy of Design, National Society of Painters in Casein, Inc., Society of American Graphic Artists); and a number of publications (Disk, Europa, The Front, The Menorah Journal, New Masses, Opinion, Rebel Poets, Transition). A selected name index to the correspondence follows the box list.
Artwork (Box 1) includes cover art, photographs and reproductions. Cover art consists of a cover for Der Hammer (in Yiddish). Arranged alphabetically by the titles supplied by Lozowick, the photographs range in subject from still-lifes to city-scapes, and from depictions of the laboring class to his hard-edged precisionist work, reflective of the 1920s fascination with machine-age technology. Also included in the collection are a number of photographs of Lozowick's work in the theatre, for which he designed both stage sets and costumes. Among the reproductions of Lozowick's work are those which appeared from 1926 through 1973 in publications as diverse as Creative Art, Harpers Magazine, The London Studio, The Menorah Journal, The Print Collector's Quarterly, and Theatre Arts Monthly.
Among the Writings (Box 2) are both manuscript and published materials. Manuscript writings include "Glossolalia" and several chapters of "Survivor From a Dead Age," autobiographical selections which illuminate Lozowick's childhood in Russia and early education. Published writings include Lozowick's essays on art and the theatre, poetry, and book reviews for Art News, The Menorah Journal, and The Nation.
Memorabilia (Box 2-5) encompasses articles about Lozowick, awards and membership cards, exhibition materials, lecture invitations, and a letter of introduction and photograph identifying Lozowick as a Russian correspondent for the periodical Broom.
The four boxes of exhibition materials (Boxes 2-5) constitute the largest portion of the collection and spans more than fifty years, including announcements, invitations, catalogs, and posters.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Artwork is subdivided by type; within that, photographs are arranged alphabetically, using the titles supplied by Lozowick. Writings is divided into manuscript and published items; published items are arranged chronologically. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type and (where possible) chronologically within each type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Abernethy, M. A. (Milton A.); Adamic, Louis, 1899-1951.; Arms, John Taylor, 1887-1953.; Arvin, Newton, 1900-1963.; Broadd, Harry A.; Burliuk, David, 1882-1967.; Calverton, V. F. (Victor Francis), 1900-1940.; Chagall, Marc, 1887-1985.; Christensen, Erwin O. (Erwin Ottomar), 1890-1976.; Conroy, Jack, 1898-1990.; Cook, Howard Norton, 1901-1980.; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964.; Dreier, Katherine Sophie, 1877-1952.; Fabri, Ralph, 1894-; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Hurwitz, Henry, 1886-1961.; Jourdan, Albert.; Kunitz, Joshua, 1896-1980.; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947.; Léger, Fernand, 1881-1955.; Lozowick, Louis, 1892-1973.; Mechlin, Leila.; Moholy-Nagy, László, 1895-1946.; Neumann, J. B.; Ostrowsky, Abbo.; Picken, George.; Putnam, Samuel, 1892-1950.; Reed, Alma M.; Schoolman, Regina.; Schwarz, Karl, 1885-1962.; Stern, Bernhard Joseph, 1894-1956.; Waite, Marjorie Peabody.; Ward, Lynd, 1905-1985.; Weber, Max, 1881-1961.; Wilson, Sol.; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-1975.; American Federation of Arts.; American Russian Institute.; Artists for Victory, Inc.; Federal Art Project.; Municipal Art Committee (New York, N.Y.); Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); National Academy of Design (U.S.); National Society of Painters in Casein, Inc.; Society of American Graphic Artists, Inc.; United States. -- Dept. of the Treasury.; Broom.; Menorah journal.; Transition.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art critics -- United States.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Jews, American.; Lithographers -- United States.; Lithography -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Russian Americans.; Articles.; Autobiographies (literary works); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Art critics.; Artists.; Lithographers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Louis Lozowick, 1963, 1967, 1974.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1923-1973; undated; 11 folders (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Cover art
    - Der Hammer, July 1928 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - By title of work, A-Z, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Theatre arts (Box 1)
    - Theatre arts (oversize), 3 photographs (Oversize 1)
  - Reproductions
    - Miscellaneous, 1926-1973; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Manuscripts
    - Autobiography
      - "Glossolalia", typescript (Box 2)
      - "Survivor From a Dead Age" (alternate title: Survivor From a Dead Past"), typescripts; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Outline, notes, typescripts (Box 2)
  - Published
    - Essays, 1926-1933; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Poetry, 1922 (Box 2)
    - Reviews, 1928-1962 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about, 1923-1973 (Box 2)
  - Awards, membership cards (Box 2)
  - Exhibition announcements, invitations (Box 2)
  - Exhibition catalogs
  - Exhibition posters, 1920s-1930s; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Exhibition posters, 1940-1952; 11 folders (Box 3)
  - Exhibition posters, 1953-1959; 11 folders (Box 4)
  - Exhibition posters, 1960-1969; 13 folders (Box 5)
  - Exhibition posters, 1970s; undated; 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Exhibition posters, 1927; 1928; 2 posters (Oversize 1)
  - Lecture invitations, publicity - Artists Union of New York, 1 poster (Oversize 1)
  - Letter of introduction with photograph identifying Lozowick as a Broom correspondent (Box 6)
  - Publicity (book) (Box 6)
  - Miscellany (Box 6)
Selected index to correspondence
A.C.A. Gallery 1945 Sept. 14
Abernethy, Milton A. 1931 Feb. 22
Ad Hoc Committee to Lift Ban on The Nation 1950 Feb. 21
Adamic, Louis 1932 Feb. 27
All America Magazine 1930 July 29
American Federation of Arts 1929 July 20 1929 Sept. 11 1930 Oct. 15 1931 May 5 1932 Jan. 19 1945 June 15 1950 July 5 undated
American Institute of Graphic Arts 1946 May 6
American Russian Institute 1931 Mar. 12 1931 Mar. 16 1931 Apr. 9 1936 Oct. 15 1936 Oct. 21
American Society of Painters, Sculptors and Gravers 1936 Jan. 9 1936 Mar.
Ames, Elizabeth 1956 Mar. 5
Arms, John Taylor 1950 Feb. 20 1950 June 19 1951 Jan. 31 undated
Art Association of Indianapolis, Indiana 1946 Apr. 3 1946 Apr. 18
Art Institute of Chicago 1930 Dec. 8 1930 Dec. 10
Artists for Victory, Inc. 1944 Apr. 11 1945 Jan. 29 1945 June 4
Arvin, Newton 1930 Sept. 17 1932 Jan. 22
Barr, Alfred H. See Museum of Modern Art (New York)
Berkshire Museum 1931 Dec. 1931 Dec. 21 1932 Jan. 4
Biddle, George 1950 Feb. 21
Black, MacKnight 1926 Feb. 25
Breckinridge, Henry (Mrs.) See Municipal Art Committee (New York, N.Y)
Broad, Harry A. 1944 May 1 undated
Burliuk, David 1947 Mar. 16 1955 Jan. 17 1956 Mar. 24 1962 Oct. 22
Calverton, Victor Francis 1930 Apr. 18 undated
Chagall, Marc 1928
Christensen, Erwin O. 1931 Mar. 27 1932 Jan. 19
Cincinnati Museum Association 1929 Mar. 29
Conroy, Jack 1930 May 2
Contempo 1931 Feb. 22
Cook, Howard undated
Crisp, Arthur 1945 June 4 1945 Oct. 30
Davis, Stuart 1936 May 25
Disk 1923 Nov. 27
Dreier, Katherine S. 1928 Oct. 15
Du Von, Jay 1930 Dec. 3
Educational Alliance 1942 Oct. 9 1944 May 31 1946 Feb. 11 1946 Dec. 31
Egbert, Donald 1962 May 9
Eichenberg, Fritz 1946 May 6
Europa 1932 Aug. 17
Fabri, Ralph 1951 Feb. 11 1963 Mar. 26
Federal Art Project 1935 Nov. 25
Frank, Waldo 1932 Mar.
The Front 1930 Dec. 3
Samson Gideon Memorial Association 1929 Dec. 12
Gussow, Bernard undated
Harper & Brothers 1926 Jan. 6
John Herron Art Institute See Art Association of Indianapolis, Indiana
Hobson, Thayer 1928 Aug. 24
The Hound & Horn Inc. 1931 Feb. 25
Hughes, Langston 1931 Mar. 28
Hurwitz, Henry See The Menorah Journal
Jourdan, Albert 1928 Nov. 13
Kozlenko, William 1932 Aug. 17
Kunitz, Joshua 1932 Aug. 31
LaGuardia, Fiorello 1935 Jan. 2
Léger, Fernand 1927 Oct. 22
Mandel, Howard 1964 May 30
Mechlin, Leila See American Federation of Arts
The Menorah Journal 1931 Dec. 11 1935 Apr. 15 1944 May 4 1947 May 6 1947 May 29 1947 Oct. 27 1947 Dec. 8 1948 Mar. 19 1948 Apr. 6 1948 Apr. 24
Moholy-Nagy, László 1928 Oct. 19
Municipal Art Committee (New York, N.Y.) 1935 Nov. 7 1935 Nov. 27 1935 Dec. 9 1935 Dec. 13 1936 Mar. 10 1936 May 31 (outgoing) 1936 June 5 1936 June 12 1936 June 30 1936 July 9 (outgoing) undated
Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.) 1931 Mar. 27 1932 Feb. 8 1935 Jan. 16 1936 July 1 1946 Jan. 17 1946 Jan. 26 1946 Feb. 1 1961 June 15
Museum Tel-Aviv See Schwarz, Karl
The Nation 1929 Apr. 22
National Academy of Design 1948 Feb. 14 1971 Oct. 5 (photocopy) 1972 Mar. 10 (photocopy) 1972 Apr. 4 (photocopy)
National Committee to Aid Striking Miners Fighting Starvation 1932 Mar.
National Society of Painters in Casein, Inc. 1963 Mar. 26 1964 May 30 1965 Feb. 12 1969 Oct. 23
Neumann, J. B. 1932 Mar. 22
New Jersey State Museum 1950 Apr. 21 1952 Dec. 1 1953 Dec. 23 1954 Jan. 13 1959 July 8 1959 Sept. 30
New Masses 1932 Mar. 21
Newark Museum 1952 Mar. 10 1957 Oct. 21 1958 May 8
Norfolk Museum 1952 Feb. 1 1952 Feb. 18
Oakland Art Gallery 1946 Nov. 2
Ohio State University Association 1942 Apr. 11 1942 July 15
Opinion 1931 Nov. 11
Ostrowsky, Abbo See Educational Alliance
Pardee, Allena 1932 June 27 1932 July 8 undated
Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts 1944 Dec. 4
Picken, George 1944 Jan. 25
Portland Art Association 1929 Apr. 8 1929 July 12 1929 Oct. 16
Portrait of America Exhibition and Competition 1945 June 4 1945 Oct. 30
Princeton Print Club 1942 Nov. 16 1943 Mar. 25
Print Club (Philadelphia) 1930 Jan. 19 1947 Jan. 29 1953 Jan. 12
The Print Collector's Quarterly 1942 Apr. 18
Public Utilities Fortnightly 1930 Aug. 2
Putnam, Samuel 1935 Nov. 25 undated
Rebel Poets 1930 May 2
Reed, Alma 1933 Aug. 14
Schoolman, Regina 1946 Mar. 26 1946 June 25 (outgoing) 1946 Nov. 6 (outgoing) 1946 Nov. 12
Schwarz, Karl 1935 July 2 1947 Aug. 6 1947 Sept. 9 1948 May 3
Seward, C. A. 1930 Sept. 10
Slater, Lo 1945 Nov. 27
Société Anonyme See Dreier, Katherine S.
Society of American Etchers, Gravers, Lithographers, and Woodcutters See Society of American Graphic Artists, Inc.
Society of American Graphic Artists, Inc. 1948 Oct. 1 1950 June 19 1951 Jan. 31 1951 Feb. 16 1956 Apr. 25 1957 Feb. 28 1957 June 8 1962 Feb. 12 1969 May 16 undated
Soyer, Moses [1973] photocopy.
Soyer, Raphael 1973 Sept. 10 (photocopy)
Stern, Bernhard J. 1945 Dec. 19 1946 Jan. 26 1946 Apr. 23
Sterne, Katharine Grant 1929 Apr. 14
Teige, Charles 1923 Nov. 27
Toledo Museum of Art 1929 Dec. 12
Transition 1928 Dec. 12 1929 Apr. 5
Treasury Relief Art Project. See United States Treasury Department
United States Treasury Department 1935 Nov. 20 1935 Nov. 26 1936 Jan. 15 1936 Apr. 23 1936 May 5 1936 July 8 1936 July 22 1936 Sept. 1 1936 Oct. 14 1936 Oct. 21 1937 July 26 1937 Oct. 14
Vassar College 1932 Feb. 5 1932 Feb. 19 1932 Mar. 14
Waite, Marjorie Peabody 1929 Nov. 9 1930 Jan. 31 1931 Nov. 19
Walker Art Center 1960 Jan. 7 1960 Dec. 6 1961 Nov. 30 1961 Dec. 4
Ward, Lynd 1956 Apr. 25 1957 Feb. 28 undated
Waters, Herbert 1957 June 20
Weber, Max 1945 Mar. 19 1951 Jan. 17 1956 Aug. 31 1957 Feb. 28
Wellington, Grace 1931 Feb. 14
Western Association of Art Museum Directors 1929 Nov. 12 1930 Apr. 15
Wilson, Sol 1961 Jan. 15
Yaddo 1956 5 Mar.
Young, Art [1940 Dec.] 1941 Dec. 29
Zigrosser, Carl 1930 Mar. 29 1935 Oct. 2 1943 May 25